[MUSIC]
P-Curve
In this lecture we'll talk about P-curve Analysis.
這一講介紹P-Curve分析
A recently developed math analytical tool that allows you to judge
這是最近發展出來，
用來評估一系列文獻證據力的工具
the evidential value is sets of study in the published literature.
這是最近發展出來，
用來評估一系列文獻證據力的工具
What do p-values look like from 100 studies where there is no true effect?
第三週曾預告一百項沒有真實效果的研究結果
用P-Curve分析的模樣
We've discussed this in an earlier lecture.
第三週曾預告一百項沒有真實效果的研究結果
用P-Curve分析的模樣
If you remember correctly,
你還記得的話
p-values are uniformly distributed if there's no true effect.
那些研究的p值是均勻分佈
Now if you've watched enough medical series,
如果你看過大量醫學文獻
you know that the flat line is no good news, right?
就會知道平坦的曲線不是好事
So in this case, if we see a p-value distribution,
一系列文獻的p值分佈呈現均勻分配的話
表示沒什麼值得探討的東西
that's uniformly distributed then nothing is going on.
一系列文獻的p值分佈呈現均勻分配的話
表示沒什麼值得探討的東西
What do p-values look like from 100 studies where there is a true effect?
那麼100項沒有真實效果的研究結果p值分佈是什麼樣子？
Well in this case we know that the p-value distribution depends on the statistical
我們已經知道p值分佈與統計檢定力有關
power of the test.
In general we can expect more low p-values around 0.01 for
一般而言，文獻中最常看到的p值是.01到.05之間
example then high p-values around 0.05.
Even though all these p-values are statistically significant, they're all
即使所有p值都指出統計顯著的結果
smaller than 0.05 they're not all equally likely if there is a true effect.
小於.05也不能保證確實有效果存在
We should find low p-values more
often than relatively high p-values.
除非偏低的p值數量多於偏高的p值
P-curve analysis allows you to test whether a set of p-values has
P-Curve分析能檢驗一系列p值的證據力
evidential value.
In this case evidential value is defined as does the p-value distribution
那麼證據力應該是指沒有真實效果時，
p值分佈近似均勻分配
look more like a uniform distribution, where there's no true effect, or
那麼證據力應該是指沒有真實效果時，
p值分佈近似均勻分配？
more like a p-value distribution where these is a true effect?
還是有真實效果時，p值分佈近似均勻分配？
An important benefit of P-curve analysis is that it's a key to the file-drawer.
P-curve最吸引人的特點是能評估抽屜效應
The test is only performed on p values smaller than 0.05.
就算分析內容只有小於0.05的p值
Given publication bias,
因為出版偏誤的緣故
where we know studies are much more likely to be published when they
統計顯著的研究比統計不顯著的研究更容易被發表
are statistically significant, than when they are not statistically significant.
An important benefit of P-Curve analysis is that you only need
P-Curve分析的優點是就算資料都是統計顯著的
the statistically significant study results to perform the test.
So you can perform it even though there is publication bias and
也能讓文獻的出版偏誤現形
that's a huge important benefit.
這是P-Curve引起注意的一大亮點
Another useful thing about P-curve analysis is that you can
P-Curve分析的另一個好處是不需要安裝統計軟體
perform the test online, you don't need any statistical software.
到官網輸入資料就能完成
Go to the online test, enter test statistics and
在網頁中輸入要分析的檢定方法
perform all the required calculations.
還有必要的統計數值就好
The question we're trying to address with a p-curve analysis is
P-Curve分析回答的首要問題是
does the p-value distribution look like one with, or one without a true effect.
有真實效果和沒有真實效果的p值分佈
看起來會不會一樣？
A good moment to perform a p-curve analysis is before you set out
最好的檢驗方法是拿設計研究的參考文獻試試看
to build on studies in the published literature.
You might want to know whether this studies in the public
可以先了解這些文獻能被發表出來
literature are just there due to publication bias, and
是因為出版偏誤
they are all basically type one errors, there's no true effect.
還是被型一錯誤膨脹出來的虛假效應
Or whether the results look robust enough to build on.
也可以檢討這些研究結果夠不夠穩定
So we're trying to differentiate between these two possible p-value distributions,
了解P-Curve分析結果的首要功課是區辨兩種p值分佈
uniform or what's known as ride scheme.
均勻分佈和正偏態分佈
The green line in this case illustrates a true effect.
綠線是有真實效果的P-Curve
Now let's take a look at an example.
我們用這個實例進一步說明
I perform the p-curve analyze of two related lines of research.
下一張展示兩個項研究的P-Curve
On the one hand elderly priming studies and
一項是"老年印象"促發
on the other hand professor priming studies.
另一項是“教授印象”促發
Now the evidence in these studies was debated
這兩項研究過去一直存在難以再現的爭議
by the publication of field replication studies.
Some people responded to these field replications by indicating that there
原研究者對再現不易的回應是
are many, many different studies in the literature that show related effects.
已經存在許多類似效果且正面支持的文獻
Now this is a valid reply, except that if you want to say that there's evidence
雖然這樣的回應有理，但是要檢視相關文獻證據力
in the published literature, then you need to quantify this.
最好能呈現數據說明
You can do this either by performing traditional data analysis or
可以用傳統的資料分析方法
you can perform a p-curve analysis and that's what I did in this case.
或者用這一講介紹的P-Curve
Now this is the P-Curve analysis for
Elderly Priming Studies.
黑色實線是"老年印象"促發的P-Curve
ElderyPpriming examines the idea that if you expose most people to elderly related
"老年印象"促發是讓參與者持續看有關老年的字詞
words, such as engl, grey or Florida, this will influence their behavior.
像是"灰頭髮"和“佛羅里達州”
行為就會被影響
More specifically, it will influence their walking speed.
特別之處是參與者的走路速度會變慢
The idea being that elderly people walk more slowly.
符合老年人走路慢的想法
So, people who were primed with elderly related words
這系列的原始研究發現讀老年相關字詞的參與者
would walk more slowly to an elevator than people in the control condition.
走向出口電梯的速度比控制組慢
If we take a look at the p-value distribution of the studies in
現在來看這一系列研究結果的p值分佈
the literature, we see that the p-value distribution is not uniformly distributed,
這條分佈既不是均勻分配
it's not right-skewed.
也不是正偏態分配
Now, actually, we see that a lot of these P-values are only barely significant.
多數研究結果的p值只是剛好顯著
This is not an indication that the studies published in the literature provide
這一系列研究的結果實際上無法充分支持假設
support for the hypothesis.
The hypothesis might still be true, but the data that we have available
假設或許是對的，但是文獻資料無法說服所有讀者
效應確實存在
does not give us any reason to believe that this is a true effect.
假設或許是對的，但是文獻資料無法說服所有讀者
效應確實存在
Now let's take at look professor priming studies.
接著來看“教授印象”促發的研究
In this line of research, people are asked to think about a professor, or
這一系列研究的實驗組參與者要想像自己是一位教授
in the control condition, they're asked to think about a group that's stereotypically
對比控制組的參與者
想像自己是比較不常動腦的樣板人物
seen as less intelligent such as soccer hooligans.
像是啦啦隊員
The idea in this study is that participants who thought about a professor
原始想法是想像自己是教授的參與者
are more likely to perform better on a general knowledge test,
做常識測驗的表現會比
such as trivial pursuit, than people in the control condition.
控制組的參與者更好
If we look at the P-value distribution, in this case, the distribution is very
這系列研究的p值分佈
similar to that that we would expect when there is a true effect.
非常接近存在真實效應的分配
Now this illustrates how useful it is to perform a p-curve analysis
這兩個例子示範P-Curve如何幫助我們
before you want to build on studies in the published literature.
選擇真正有參考價值的文獻
Let's say that you're interested in priming effects, would you build on
如果你想設計類似的促發效應研究
elderly priming research, or would you build on professor priming research?
應該參考"老年印象"，還是“教授印象”？
Now, these p-curve analyses do not prove that professor priming is a real effect,
雖然P-Curve不能直接指出“教授印象”有真實效果
and elderly priming is not a real effect.
"老年印象"沒有真實效果
But if you're thinking about doing research on priming, and
如果你想設計促發實驗
you have to decide between these two research areas, then it's a much better
有必要從兩種研究模式選擇一種
而P-Curve可以告訴你
bet to build on professor priming related studies than elderly priming studies.
選"教授印象"的勝算較大
You can also use p-curve analysis for small sets of p-values.
少量的p值也可以用P-Curve分析
You have to take a little care, when you have a small number of observations,
只是要稍微注意一下
資料不多的時候
you have low statistical power for any test, also for a p-curve analysis.
統計檢定力必定偏低
P-Curve分析也會受限
But sometimes, the data is so clear that even with a small set of studies,
不過有時候少量研究的資料非常清楚
you can prevent yourself from following up on reliable research.
可以確保分析的可信度
Let's take an example.
來看看這個實例
In this publication, researchers look at the effect of reading literary fiction.
這篇論文研究閱讀小說的效用
On Theory of Mind, how much do you, for example, empathize with other people?
根據心智理論，研究者想問小說讀者會不會更有同理心
The researchers performed five studies, and
論文作者執行了五項研究
they provided table with a critical test results for each study.
所有結果的分析總結在一張表格裡
We're always interested in the main effect of condition and
因為要探討的是組間的主要效果
I've highlighted the test results here.
我把檢定結果標示出來
We can see that for the first study they observed a p-value of 0.01.
由上面開始看到第一個研究的p值是0.01
For the second they have observed the p-value of 0.08.
第二個研究的p值是0.08
This test result will be ignored by
the p-curve analysis because it only
由於不小於0.05
這項p值在P-Curve分析裡會被忽略
focuses on p-values smaller than 0.05.
由於不小於0.05
這項p值在P-Curve分析裡會被忽略
Now for the remaining three studies,
其他三個研究的p值
we see p values of 0.04, 0.04, and 0.04.
分別都是0.04
Let's perform a p-curve analysis on this data set.
來看看P-Curve分析的結果
We can see that the p-value distribution is not
這條P-Curve表示並沒有真實效果存在
as you would expect if there is a true effect.
And indeed the statistical test tells us that the evidential
統計檢定的結果其實指出這些研究的證據力並不充分
value of the set up studies, if any, is inadequate.
This does not mean that the theory is false and could still be true but
這不是說理論是錯的，而且以後有可能翻盤
the data we have available in this publication
但是這些已發表的資料無法支持研究者的假設
does not allow us to conclude that the hypothesis is supported.
The reason that I'm giving this example is not that I want to point
我拿這篇論文說明，並不是指出
out that some people publish set of studies that are not reliable, it happens.
這篇論文的作者研究品質信度不高
This is very important for you to know that you can use p-curve
重點是讓你知道P-Curve可以評估一系列研究結果
的可信程度
analysis to identify sets of studies that are less reliable than others.
重點是讓你知道P-Curve可以評估一系列研究結果
的可信程度
When I was presenting about p-curve analysis in workshop I taught,
在我曾親自主持的工作坊教授P-Curve分析時
one of the PhD students in the room
當時有位博士生立刻用這篇論文做P-Curve分析
was performing a p-curve analysis on exactly this set of studies.
This PhD student was trying to replicate these studies for over a year but
這位博士生一直嘗試再現研究結果
had been unsuccessful.
但始終不能成功
So I think it's very important to perform a p-curve of analysis before you try to
所以P-Curve分析也許是做文獻回顧的好幫手
build on studies in the literature.
Because otherwise you might waste a year trying to build on research that is not as
也許能幫你省下投入低信度研究的時間
reliable as you think.
Now remember when a p-curve analysis says that
請記得即使P-Curve分析指出一系列研究
a set of study lacks evidential value, the theory might still be true.
缺乏證據力，研究背後的理論還有可能是真的
The data just don't provide evidence for the theory.
資料無法做理論的直接證據
P-curve analysis allows you to test whether a set of studies in the published
P-Curve分析可以檢測一系列文獻的p值
literature yields a p-value distribution that looks more like the one you
到底接近存在真實效果，還是沒有真實效果
would expect when there is a true effect, than when there is no true effect.
Using p-curve analysis before you decide to build on studies on the published
閱讀設計研究有關的文獻時
literature might allow you to see how robust these findings are.
P-Curve分析可以評估結果的穩定度
And prevents you from building an unreliable results.
避免製造低信度的結果
[MUSIC]
影片結束